<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jcalpickard.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://jcalpickard.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-09-11T14:58:40-05:00</updated><id>https://jcalpickard.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">⧉</title><subtitle>Notes and log entries.</subtitle><author><name>Justin Pickard</name></author><entry><title type="html">Procedural portraits (2): Empathy and innovation in ‘Eno’</title><link href="https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/08/21/procedural-portraits-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Procedural portraits (2): Empathy and innovation in ‘Eno’" /><published>2024-08-21T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-09-11T14:58:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/08/21/procedural%20portraits-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/08/21/procedural-portraits-2/"><![CDATA[<h6 id="in-the-previous-post-i-explored-the-distinctive-structure-of-eno-2024-a-generative-documentary-about-brian-eno-in-this-second-part-i-examine-how-this-generative-structure-fosters-a-sense-of-procedural-empathy-and-consider-its-implications-for-documentary-filmmaking-and-our-understanding-of-creative-processes">[<em>In <a href="https://justinpickard.net/log/2024/08/17/procedural-portraits-1/" class="web-link">the previous post</a>, I explored the distinctive structure of ‘Eno’ (2024), a generative documentary about <a href="https://www.brian-eno.net/" class="web-link">Brian Eno</a>. In this second part, I examine how this generative structure fosters a sense of ‘procedural empathy’, and consider its implications for documentary filmmaking and our understanding of creative processes.</em>]</h6>

<blockquote>
  <p>‘Characters or social actors may come and go, offering information, giving testimony, providing evidence. Places and things may appear and disappear as they are brought forward in support of the film’s point of view. A logic of implication bridges these leaps from one person or place to another.’
<cite>— Bill Nicols, <em>Introduction to Documentary</em>, Third Edition (2017)</cite></p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="procedural-empathy">Procedural empathy</h2>

<p>The interplay of elements in ‘Eno’ not only shapes the documentary’s structure, but also fosters a singular viewing experience. The film’s generative structure allows viewers to experience Eno’s creative process as if from the inside, providing a deeper understanding than documentaries typically offer.</p>

<p>Writer and game designer <a href="https://bogost.com/" class="web-link">Ian Bogost</a> introduced the idea of ‘procedural rhetoric’ to describe how systems, particularly video games, make arguments. He argues that games and other procedural systems can make strong claims about how the world works through the processes they embody and the models they construct.<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote web-link" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> The art of ‘persuading through processes’ (computational or otherwise), procedural rhetoric encompasses processes as arguments, simulation as persuasion, and creators’ ideological expression through system design.</p>

<p>Where Bogost’s focus was on argumentation, ‘Eno’ extends procedural rhetoric into emotional engagement, fostering what we might call a ‘procedural empathy’ for its subject. Shifting focus from the system’s argument to its emotional and cognitive <em>effects</em>, the transition from rhetoric to empathy is not a leap, but a natural extension of Bogost’s ideas. Just as procedural rhetoric uses systems to make arguments, procedural empathy leverages these same systems to foster emotional understanding.</p>

<p>Originating from the German ‘<em>Einfühlung</em>’ (literally ‘feeling into’), the concept of empathy has undergone significant shifts over time. Initially, it evoked an aesthetics of ‘mirroring and analogy’ (<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/1329878X17726794" class="web-link">※</a>) where viewers would project themselves into objects, blurring the lines between the self and the observed form. But over the twentieth century, the concept shifted towards social cognition and interpersonal understanding, becoming central to discussions of how we relate to others and the world around us (<a href="https://yalebooks.yale.edu/book/9780300222685/empathy/" class="web-link">※</a>).</p>

<p><a href="https://files.justinpickard.net/images/log/2024/08/eno-music-for-airports-notation-2.jpg" class="web-link"><img class="img-padded" src="https://files.justinpickard.net/images/log/2024/08/eno-music-for-airports-notation-2.jpg" alt="Graphic score, tracks from Eno's ‘Music for Airports’ (1978)"></a></p>

<p>Today, empathy is commonly understood as the capacity to grasp and share the feelings of another subject. Where traditional documentary films seek to evoke this kind of empathy through narrative storytelling, ‘Eno’ takes a different approach. Rather than simply depicting Brian Eno’s experiences, it creates a system that mimics the generative qualities of his work, allowing viewers to ‘feel into’ his methods directly. This approach aligns with early conceptions of empathy as a means to penetrate objects’ interiors, but applies them instead to systems thinking and the creative process.</p>

<p>This procedural empathy can be seen as an evolution of Bogost’s ‘procedural enthymeme’<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote web-link" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>, where the audience is expected to fill in the missing pieces of the argument. In ‘Eno’, viewers complete their understanding of Eno’s creative process through (knowingly) engaging with the film’s generative structure, supporting a deeper empathetic connection. As audiences experience different versions of the documentary, they come to understand the unpredictability and serendipity that characterises Eno’s creative process. The film doesn’t just tell viewers about Eno’s methods; it allows them to experience a version of those methods firsthand. Two key sequences illustrate this approach:</p>

<h3 id="do-nothing-emulating-oblique-strategies">Do nothing: Emulating <em>Oblique Strategies</em>
</h3>

<p>How can a film emulate a deck of cards? Created by Eno and Peter Schmidt in 1975, <em><a href="http://music.hyperreal.org/artists/brian_eno/osfaq2.html" class="web-link">Oblique Strategies</a></em> is a deck of cards with instructions and gnomic phrases designed to break creative blocks and spur lateral thinking (<a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b02qncrt" class="web-link">※</a>). These cards have become an iconic tool in Eno’s creative process, embodying his interest in chance operations and systemic approaches to art-making. The value of the deck is illustrated by an anecdote about Eno’s work with David Bowie on the ‘Heroes’ album. During recording, each drew a card without revealing it to the other. Eno’s card read ‘Try to make everything as similar as possible,’ while Bowie’s instructed him to ‘Emphasise differences.’ The creative tension born of these contradictory prompts led to rapid, dynamic changes in their collaborative process, demonstrating how chance-based constraints can spark unexpected outcomes.</p>

<p>In one newly-shot sequence in my ‘Eno’ screening, artist and musician <a href="https://laurieanderson.com/" class="web-link">Laurie Anderson</a>, one of Eno’s long-time collaborators, draws a card that reads, simply: ‘Do nothing for as long as possible.’ Following this card’s instructions, Anderson sits in silence, looking straight down the camera lens. After an uncomfortably long pause, the scene shifts, triggering a sequence linked by ideas of absence, silence, and nothingness. This is one of a dozen possible cards shot (six drawn by Anderson, and a further six drawn by David Byrne). The draw is a branch point, with any of the twelve outcomes pivoting the film’s direction. By recreating the process of drawing and ‘following’ an <em>Oblique Strategies</em> prompt, ‘Eno’ doesn’t just inform viewers about Eno’s methods – it allows them to experience an analogous process of constrained, chance-driven creativity. Each viewing of the film becomes a ‘draw’ from its database, fostering procedural empathy by allowing viewers to engage with Eno’s creative process in a singularly immersive way.</p>

<p><a href="https://files.justinpickard.net/images/log/2024/08/eno-oblique-strategies.png" class="web-link"><img class="img-padded" src="https://files.justinpickard.net/images/log/2024/08/eno-oblique-strategies.png" alt="Selection from my own Oblique Strategies deck, long mislaid"></a></p>

<h3 id="in-the-name-of-love-depicting-creativity">‘In The Name of Love’: Depicting creativity</h3>

<p>Another striking example is in the film’s depiction of Eno’s collaborative work. This sequence is particularly powerful as it combines intimate, contemporary footage with archival material to illustrate the full arc of Eno’s creative process. It begins with new footage of Eno revisiting his collection of microcassettes, which he has long used to capture initial song ideas. He explains his non-linear approach to songwriting, emphasising the importance of capturing fleeting ideas and the iterative nature of the creative process. As he listens to these tapes, we see him cringing with a mix of amusement and embarrassment.</p>

<p>The film then transitions to archival footage of Eno in the studio with U2. We witness young Bono scat-improvising melodies, details of Eno’s direction, and the other band members’ confused-but-game reactions. This demonstrates Eno’s role as a facilitator of creativity in others. As the session progresses, viewers observe the halting emergence of the now-iconic guitar riff and vocal melody of ‘<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LHcP4MWABGY" class="web-link">Pride (In The Name of Love)</a>’. By presenting these elements in sequence, ‘Eno’ creates a temporal bridge. This allows viewers to directly experience the uncertainty of early ideas, the vulnerability of sharing those ideas, and the collaborative effort required to bring them to fruition. That the studio footage features U2, a band that has achieved massive success, adds weight to the film’s argument. It demonstrates the cultural impact of Eno’s unconventional methods, highlighting the power of his collaborative approach to creativity.</p>

<h3 id="beyond-the-empathy-machine">Beyond the empathy machine</h3>

<p>In both of these sequences, ‘Eno’ creates procedural empathy by modeling key aspects of Eno’s creative process. Rather than simply describing these processes, the film emulates them, allowing viewers to experience analogous versions of Eno’s creative journey. This approach creates a correspondence between the viewer’s experience and Eno’s methods, enabling viewers to develop a more intuitive, experiential understanding of his creative worldview.</p>

<p>Virtual reality has been hailed as an ‘<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iXHil1TPxvA" class="web-link">ultimate empathy machine</a>’, a framing and approach popularised by artist <a href="http://milk.co/bio.html" class="web-link">Chris Milk</a>. This approach relies on immersive sensory experiences to simulate ‘being someone else.’<sup id="fnref:3" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote web-link" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> From the vantage of 2024, Milk’s vision of VR’s potential to create empathy by simulating others’ experiences seems wildly naïve – not least the idea that showing VR films of Syrian refugees’ experiences to Davos attendees could have a meaningful impact. However, Milk’s earlier work did create affecting experiences. I vividly recall encountering his <a href="https://experiments.withgoogle.com/the-wilderness-downtown" class="web-link">HTML5 interactive short</a> for Arcade Fire’s ‘The Wilderness Downtown’ in 2010, which felt genuinely revolutionary at the time.<sup id="fnref:4" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote web-link" rel="footnote">4</a></sup></p>

<p><a href="https://files.justinpickard.net/images/log/2024/08/wilderness-downtown.jpg" class="web-link"><img class="img-padded" src="https://files.justinpickard.net/images/log/2024/08/wilderness-downtown.jpg" alt="Screenshot from Chris Milk’s HTML5 interactive short for Arcade Fire’s ‘The Wilderness Downtown’"></a></p>

<p>While VR can provide immediate experiences, it often struggles to build lasting empathy. A focus on fleeting, high-fidelity moments comes at the expense of deeper cognitive and contextual engagement. However, ‘Eno’ may succeed where VR’s promises have fallen short. Rather than projecting viewers into Brian Eno’s body or immediate physical environment, the film creates a conceptual space where viewers can engage with the procedures and systems that have shaped his work. By aligning viewers with its subject through structural mimicry and engagement, ‘Eno’ demonstrates that empathy need not rely on sensory immersion.</p>

<p>While ‘Eno’ surpasses VR’s limitations in creating empathy for its subject, it also diverges from standard documentary approaches. Documentary film can itself be seen as an ‘empathy machine’, an earlier ‘attempt to make sensible to oneself the emotional experience of another via technology’ (<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/1329878X17726794" class="web-link">※</a>). From its inception, the genre has sought to bring viewers into the lives and experiences of others, fostering understanding and emotional connection through narrative techniques and visual storytelling. Challenging these earlier documentary conventions, ‘Eno’ uses media archives and database logic to compose a possibility space – a dynamic field where combinatorics and non-linear causalities generate emergent narratives that unfold differently with each viewing.</p>

<p>In a traditional documentary, filmmakers might have followed Eno’s career from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roxy_Music" class="web-link">Roxy Music</a> to his solo work and collaborations, sourcing and sequencing newly-shot footage, archival material, and voiceover recordings to build a coherent narrative. Reworking the relationship between filmmakers, subject, and audience, ‘Eno’ shifts some of this curatorial role to its generative system, allowing for emergent narratives that more closely mimic Eno’s own creative processes. Viewers must piece together an understanding of Eno from non-chronological fragments. This approach allows empathy to arise organically from viewer-system interaction, rather than being dictated by a fixed narrative.</p>

<h2 id="eno-as-prototype-and-provocation">‘Eno’ as prototype and provocation</h2>

<p>In its distinctive approach to documentary storytelling, ‘Eno’ serves as both a proof-of-concept and a challenge to established documentary practices, signaling potential shifts in how we create and consume non-fiction cinema. At once familiar and recognisably new, it challenges the idea of a ‘finished’ film, with the potential for ongoing updates, additional footage, and evolving narrative possibilities. The film’s dual roles as prototype and provocation are mutually reinforcing: its distinctive approach generates attention and discussion, validating its status as a prototype for future works of generative storytelling.</p>

<p>The film’s procedural empathy for Eno as a subject aligns with its structure. Eno’s work provides an ideal context for demonstrating the potential of generative filmmaking. However, Hustwit and Dawes’s co-founding of start-up <a href="https://www.anamorph.com/" class="web-link">Anamorph</a> signals their belief in ‘Eno’s’ potential beyond Eno. With a patent pending on the generative system, Anamorph positions ‘Eno’ as a viable prototype for a new form of media, ready for wider industry adoption. By allowing for dynamic, evolving narratives, Anamorph’s technology could reshape documentary production, shifting it from a fixed, linear process to something more iterative; a sustained curation of content for dynamic, on-the-fly assembly.</p>

<p><a href="https://files.justinpickard.net/images/log/2024/08/eno-mechanical-turk.jpg" class="web-link"><img class="img-padded" src="https://files.justinpickard.net/images/log/2024/08/eno-mechanical-turk.jpg" alt="Silly mash-up of the B1, from Gary Hustwit’s email newsletter, and an image from a 1789 book published by Joseph von Racknitz in an attempt to debunk the Turk"></a></p>

<p>The development of a physical interface for the Brain One software, in partnership with cult Swedish electronics company <a href="https://teenage.engineering/" class="web-link">Teenage Engineering</a>, further blurs the lines between cinema, technology demonstration, and live performance. Attracting attention from tech enthusiasts and wider creative community, this physical interface, ‘B-1’, translates the abstract concept of generative filmmaking into an interactive object. With the interface in use, the film’s ‘live’ screenings become performative demonstrations, evoking landmark tech demos like Douglas Engelbart’s ‘<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Mother_of_All_Demos" class="web-link">Mother of All Demos</a>’, or even the 18th century chess-playing <a href="https://www.atlasobscura.com/articles/object-of-intrigue-the-turk" class="web-link">Mechanical Turk</a>. While the Turk was later <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maelzel%27s_Chess_Player" class="web-link">revealed as a hoax</a>, all three examples showcase the power of live demonstrations in capturing public imagination. In deploying B-1, ‘Eno’ is not just a film or technological demo, but part of a longer tradition of performances that, like its predecessors, reshapes our sense of what’s possible.</p>

<p>As a prototype, ‘Eno’ demonstrates the feasibility and potential of generative filmmaking, offering a tangible model for future productions. However, its role as a provocation extends far beyond technical innovation. By rejecting the ‘finished’ work or preferred ‘<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Director%27s_cut" class="web-link">director’s cut</a>’, it challenges fundamental assumptions about authorship, narrative structure, and the role of the viewer. The film also prompts debate about the role of truth and representation in non-fiction storytelling, questioning whether a single, fixed narrative can capture a subject. As the industry grapples with generative technologies, ‘Eno’ not only shows how these tools can be used to enhance storytelling, but poses challenging questions about the future of the documentary, the role of the director, and the very definition of a ‘film’.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>Documentary film offers a unique perspective on its subjects, providing a commentary that goes beyond simple indexicality. ‘Eno’s’ generative structure both honours and stretches this function. By reworking the typical linkages between footage and historical events into a dynamic, algorithmically-mediated process, the film challenges our understanding of what a documentary can be.</p>

<p>‘Eno’s’ generative approach redefines the roles of filmmaker, subject, and audience. The filmmaker becomes a system designer, curating a dynamic possibility space. The subject is transformed into a dataset, yielding new insights with each viewing. Audiences, in turn, become active interpreters. By transforming Eno’s personal archive into a dynamic database and using generative software to arrange the film, ‘Eno’ demonstrates how structure and chance can coexist in documentary storytelling.</p>

<p>But the potential implications of ‘Eno’ extend beyond a single documentary. For filmmakers, the film represents a proof of concept for new narrative structures. For technologists, it demonstrates the possibilities of generative media systems. For audiences, it presents a new kind of viewing experience. And for the industry, it suggests a new product category that could reshape how we consume and engage with documentary content.</p>

<p>As both a portrait and a prototype for further media innovations, ‘Eno’ points to a future where documentaries are not static artifacts but dynamic, evolving systems. By allowing audiences to experience, and not simply observe, their subjects’ processes and prevailing contexts, such documentaries could offer more nuanced, multifaceted depictions of complex topics and individuals. Moreover, ‘Eno’ holds a mirror to the database logics of our own, increasingly algorithm-mediated lives. By making its generative processes explicit, the film encourages us to reflect on the systems that shape our daily experiences and understanding. It reminds us that our perception of reality is always partial and contingent, shaped by the mechanisms through which we encounter information.</p>

<p>Against a charged backdrop of generative media and algorithmic curation, ‘Eno’ suggests that the future of understanding may lie not in fixed narratives, but in systems that allow us to explore and experience different perspectives. Such tools for fostering procedural empathy may become not just valuable, but necessary. More than simply a (procedural) portrait of Brian Eno, the film challenges us to rethink not just how we make and consume media, but how we relate to the world around us.</p>

<p><a href="https://files.justinpickard.net/images/log/2024/08/eno-interactive.png" class="web-link"><img class="img-padded" src="https://files.justinpickard.net/images/log/2024/08/eno-interactive.png" alt="From Eno’s diary, ‘A Year with Swollen Appendices’ (1996)"></a></p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>My go-to example is ‘<a href="https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/332686/john-company-second-edition" class="web-link">John Company</a>’, a boardgame about the East India Company. The game’s systems and structures make a clear argument about exploitation and corporate power. By focusing on the incentives and internal dynamics that undergirded colonial rule, the game’s rules force players into the role of ambitious dynasts engaged in colonial trade, directly incentivising the exploitation of resources and people. By implicating players, but with the distance afforded by playing as a family rather than specific individuals, the game fosters historical and systemic understanding through personal complicity. As <a href="https://spacebiff.com/2022/11/23/john-company-3/" class="web-link">Dan Thurot explains</a>, ‘When we pillage this safer version of India, this cardboard India that will not become host to fifty million dead because of our actions, we are treated to a razz of the nerves, the thrill of embarking on a grand adventure that will transform the world beneath our grasping fingertips, and to the horror of seeing that adventure for the filigree that it is.’ This vividly illustrates how the game’s procedural rhetoric implicates players in the historical dynamics of colonialism, fostering a deeper understanding of its causes and systemic implications. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote web-link" role="doc-backlink">⤴︎</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>In classical rhetoric, an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enthymeme" class="web-link">enthymeme</a> is a syllogism with an unstated premise, which the audience is expected to fill in. By extension, a ‘procedural enthymeme’ is a set of rules or constraints in an interactive system that make an implicit argument. The user or player must work out this claim through by interacting with the system, in order to correctly manipulate or understand it. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote web-link" role="doc-backlink">⤴︎</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Anthropologist Lisa Messeri’s 2024 monograph, <em><a href="https://www.dukeupress.edu/in-the-land-of-the-unreal" class="web-link">In the Land of the Unreal</a></em>, revals that, by the time of her fieldwork with Los Angeles’s VR community in 2018, VR’s promise as an ‘empathy machine’ was already dated: ‘What good is empathy, asked one VR producer on a film festival panel, if it doesn’t translate into action? What good is empathy, asked a CEO on a start-up panel, if it doesn’t help raise venture capital (VC) money?’ <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote web-link" role="doc-backlink">⤴︎</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>But perhaps this should be no surprise. As media theorist Grant Bollmer <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/1329878X17726794" class="web-link">describes</a>, ‘The effect of [this] video is particular and nostalgic, ideally evoking memories of the viewer’s childhood … it directs the viewer back to their own memories, experiences, and the interface of the computer screen’. This introduces a further critique of the ‘empathy machine’: rather than fostering real understanding of others, such technologies often lead users to project their own experiences and existing biases. <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote web-link" role="doc-backlink">⤴︎</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Justin Pickard</name></author><category term="authorship" /><category term="creativity" /><category term="empathy" /><category term="prototypes" /><category term="documentary" /><category term="film" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[[In the previous post, I explored the distinctive structure of ‘Eno’ (2024), a generative documentary about Brian Eno. In this second part, I examine how this generative structure fosters a sense of ‘procedural empathy’, and consider its implications for documentary filmmaking and our understanding of creative processes.]]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Procedural portraits (1): Decoding ‘Eno’s’ generative structure</title><link href="https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/08/17/procedural-portraits-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Procedural portraits (1): Decoding ‘Eno’s’ generative structure" /><published>2024-08-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-09-11T14:58:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/08/17/procedural-portraits-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/08/17/procedural-portraits-1/"><![CDATA[<h6 id="this-is-the-first-of-a-two-part-exegesis-on-eno-2024-a-generative-documentary-about-musician-and-producer-brian-eno-this-first-post-focuses-on-the-documentarys-structure-and-how-it-reimagines-the-relationship-between-archive-database-and-film-in-the-second-part-ill-show-how-this-structure-fosters-a-procedural-empathy-for-its-subject-and-consider-the-implications-of-this-approach-to-documentary-filmmaking">[<em>This is the first of a two-part exegesis on ‘<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt19854690/" class="web-link">Eno</a>’ (2024), a generative documentary about musician and producer <a href="https://www.brian-eno.net/" class="web-link">Brian Eno</a>. This first post focuses on the documentary’s structure and how it reimagines the relationship between archive, database, and film. In the second part, I’ll show how this structure fosters a ‘procedural empathy’ for its subject, and consider the implications of this approach to documentary filmmaking.</em>]</h6>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TzORw1dZww8" class="web-link"><img class="img-padded" src="https://files.justinpickard.net/images/log/2024/08/eno-crosshairs.jpg" alt="Screenshot of Brian Eno's home computer setup, from the trailer for ‘Eno’ (2024)"></a></p>

<p>In this darkened cinema, Brian Eno’s home computer setup fills the screen. Dual monitors, a keyboard, knobs and dials, as he manipulates an arrangement in Logic Pro. Two concentric circles – orange and red – orbit his cursor like a target. This custom pointer, designed to improve visibility on large screens, is more than a passing detail; it’s a microcosm of ‘Eno’ (2024), a new generative documentary from director <a href="https://www.hustwit.com/" class="web-link">Gary Hustwit</a>. The cursor detail exemplifies the film’s representation of the creative process. Just as Eno’s custom cursor guides his attention through a complex digital workspace, the film’s generative structure leads viewers through his creative landscape. Unlike films that pursue empathy through narrative or visual immersion, ‘Eno’ achieves understanding through shared experience: <em>This</em>, it suggests, <em>is what it feels like to be Brian Eno</em>.</p>

<p>At the heart of this experience is ‘Brain One’, custom software developed by programmer and digital artist <a href="https://brendandawes.com/" class="web-link">Brendan Dawes</a>. Drawing from a database of archival footage and newly-shot interviews, Brain One assembles an 85-90 minute sequence for each screening. Though the film’s production predates the recent surge of attention around generative AI, it provides a fresh perspective on authorship and creativity in media. In this, ‘Eno’ serves as both prototype and provocation. It invites us to reconsider the roles of audience, creator, and technology in narrative experiences, while demonstrating the potential of generative systems to connect viewers and subjects.</p>

<p>In ‘Eno’, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_medium_is_the_message" class="web-link">the medium is the message</a>. The film’s generative structure is not a technical gimmick, but a key aspect of its portrayal of Eno’s creative philosophy. By employing a database-driven, algorithmically-assembled narrative, it embodies its subject’s longstanding interest in systems, chance operations, and non-linear creative processes. This approach ensures form and content are tightly linked, offering viewers an experience that mimics Eno’s own methodologies.</p>

<h2 id="three-modalities-archive-database-film">Three modalities: Archive, database, film</h2>

<p>The interplay of three core elements in ‘Eno’ – <em>archive</em>, <em>database</em>, and <em>film</em> – creates a singular viewing experience. By examining each element and their interactions, we can understand how ‘Eno’ takes a new approach to representing its subject’s life, engaging audiences, and constructing a narrative.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TzORw1dZww8" class="web-link"><img class="img-padded" src="https://files.justinpickard.net/images/log/2024/08/eno-listening-to-tapes.jpg" alt="Screenshot of Eno listening to personal microcasette recordings, from the trailer for ‘Eno’ (2024)"></a></p>

<h3 id="archive-as-foundation">Archive as foundation</h3>

<p>Brian Eno’s personal video archive, comprising 500 hours of footage, provides a foundation for ‘Eno’. Unlike formal institutional archives, this collection of home videos, studio sessions, live performances, and interviews captures spontaneous, unscripted moments that reveal Eno’s personality and creative process. This intimate access allows audiences to experience Eno’s work directly, while also providing a gateway to broader historical and cultural narratives. For viewers, Eno’s archive serves as a temporal reference point, connecting personal history with broader cultural milieus; from a youthful Bono and U2, to an interview with broadcaster Sandi Toksvig,<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote web-link" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> or Eno’s memories of his childhood exposure to African American music in pubs frequented by GIs stationed at US military bases in the east of England, in the aftermath of World War Two. These juxtapositions allow viewers to mentally map the interplay between personal experience and wider cultural flows.</p>

<p>Eno’s interaction with both personal and public archives, including YouTube, becomes a central theme of the film. Scenes of him revisiting old recordings demonstrate how he reinterprets and reflects on his past work. His clear frustration with YouTube’s interface (auto-loading ads met with expletives), contrasts with thoughtful reflection on personal recordings, illustrating the varied responses elicited by different archival forms. Where traditional archival practices have often prioritised preservation, ‘Eno’ approaches the archive as a dynamic, living entity, open to reinterpretation and future possibilities. This approach aligns with contemporary archival theory, which increasingly recognises archives as active sites of knowledge production. By digitising and tagging Eno’s personal archive, the film-makers have transformed it into a malleable, generative resource.</p>

<p>This transformation of Eno’s archive is crucial to realising the film’s generative structure. The resulting database serves as the film’s backbone, allowing a dynamic narrative assembly that tracks Eno’s own interests and workflows. The digitisation allows multiple narratives to emerge from the same source material, bringing archival tensions around preservation and interpretation into dialogue with the non-linear logic of the database, and shifting how we, as an audience, can interact with and derive meaning from Eno’s personal records.</p>

<p><a href="https://files.justinpickard.net/images/log/2024/08/blue-punch-card.jpg" class="web-link"><img class="img-padded" src="https://files.justinpickard.net/images/log/2024/08/blue-punch-card.jpg" alt="Front of an IBM 80-column punched card"></a></p>

<h3 id="database-as-organising-logic">Database as organising logic</h3>

<p>The transformation of Eno’s archive into a database marks a key difference in the film’s approach. While the archive provides the raw material, the database structure enables the dynamic, generative assembly of visual sequences. The transition from static repository to interactive system tracks both the film’s distinctive approach and Eno’s own creative philosophy.</p>

<p>In producing ‘Eno’, director Gary Hustwit and his team tagged each digitised clip with metadata, while paying attention to the types of scenes and possible connections between them (<a href="https://teenage.engineering/now#B-1" class="web-link">※</a>). This meticulous process not only preserves the archival material but also imbues it with new potential. Each tag becomes a point of connection, allowing the generative system to create meaningful juxtapositions and narrative threads that might not have been apparent in the original, chronological archive. Each piece of footage, each interview, each cultural touchstone is no longer a static record, but a dynamic element that can be endlessly recontextualised and recombined.</p>

<p>Reflecting an understanding of film as both information and experience, this process demonstrates what media theorist Lev Manovich calls ‘<a href="https://zeitkunst.org/media/pdf/Manovich1999.pdf" class="web-link">database logic</a>’. Unlike traditional narrative, which follows a clear, sequential cause-and-effect trajectory, database logic presents information as a collection of items, each holding equal significance. Leading scholar of literature and technology N. Katherine Hayles extends Manovich’s concept, presenting databases as sites of encounter between machine capabilities and human needs.<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote web-link" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> This perspective is particularly relevant to ‘Eno’, where the database becomes a mediating structure between algorithmic processing and Hustwit’s directorial vision.</p>

<p>The documentary’s custom Brain One software acts as both interpreter and creator, embodying Manovich’s model of user interaction with databases. It queries the database, interprets the metadata, and constructs narrative paths, effectively ‘performing’ the role of a user engaging with the archive. This process closely resembles Eno’s own methods, in which rules and randomness combine to generate unexpected outcomes.</p>

<p>This database structure fundamentally alters viewers’ relationship with the documentary. Unlike traditional films where audiences passively receive a predetermined narrative, ‘Eno’ requires active engagement. Audiences must piece together the story, drawing connections between non-chronological elements. Each viewer will focus on different aspects, based on their own interests and prevailing contexts, further personalising the experience. By leveraging database logic, ‘Eno’ suggests that our understanding of a subject can be enriched by experiencing multiple, algorithmically-generated perspectives. This approach recognises the complexity of life and creativity, resisting the simplifications often required of linear narratives.</p>

<p><a href="https://reverbmachine.com/blog/deconstructing-brian-eno-music-for-airports/" class="web-link"><img class="img-padded" src="https://files.justinpickard.net/images/log/2024/08/eno-music-for-airports-notation.jpg" alt="Graphic score, tracks from Eno's ‘Music for Airports’ (1978)"></a></p>

<h3 id="film-as-generative-performance">Film as generative performance</h3>

<p>‘Eno’ transforms its archival foundation and database logic into a dynamic, performative act. While retaining the capacity for visual storytelling and emotional resonance, it diverges from understandings of film as a fixed, repeatable medium. Instead, ‘Eno’ actively demonstrates its generative nature, making the process of creation central to the viewing experience. Blending documentary content with elements of live performance, the Brain One software dynamically assembles a new version of the film for each screening.</p>

<p>Balancing directorial intent with algorithmic unpredictability, ‘Eno’ transforms its archival foundations into a dynamic viewing experience. Fixed opening and closing scenes featuring Brian Eno provide a consistent framing device. Alongside other ‘pinned’ scenes, occurring within specific ‘regions’ of the runtime, fixed elements comprise about 25% of the film, ensuring a narrative arc while allowing for significant variability. The remaining 75% draws from a combination of edited scenes and archival material, assembled into ‘modules’ of sequenced footage.</p>

<p>Without explicit performative elements, ‘Eno’ could easily be mistaken for a traditional, linear documentary. To distinguish itself and function effectively as generative media, ‘Eno’ must <em>perform</em> its generativity. The film makes some of its underlying processes explicit through on-screen software instructions, lines of code and filenames in monospace type, and visible transitions as the software loads new material. These elements evoke the aesthetics of <a href="https://livecodingbook.toplap.org/" class="web-link">live coding</a>, where performers write and modify code in real-time. In a similar way, in ‘Eno,’ the visible process of Brain One selecting and assembling footage becomes part of the performance, ensuring the film’s generative structure does not pass unnoticed.<sup id="fnref:3" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote web-link" rel="footnote">3</a></sup></p>

<p>‘Eno’ also adopts the practice of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software_versioning" class="web-link">versioning</a>. Each screening is marked with a date and version number, situating the audience in time and space. My viewing’s title card included ‘15 July 2024’ and was labeled a ‘Picturehouse cut’, specific to the UK cinema chain where I saw it. Destabilising the normally clear boundary between content and context, for me, this prompted an awareness of my viewing being but one possible selection from the film’s database; evoking the implied totality of the film’s source material and its latent narrative possibilities.</p>

<p>‘Eno’ composes a ‘field’ of narrative possibilities, allowing viewers to experience its subject’s core, enduring identity through non-linear means. By breaking Brian Eno’s life and work into discrete, recombinant segments, the film creates a space where, as in ambient music, precise sequencing doesn’t really matter. There’s little that’s truly load-bearing, in narrative terms. Unlike traditional documentaries, where certain key scenes or information are crucial for the narrative to make sense, ‘Eno’ is designed so that most elements can be rearranged or even omitted without compromising the overall understanding of its subject. With individual moments free to assume different meanings depending on their placement within the generated sequence, the resulting algorithmic shuffling supports a cumulative depiction of Eno as an artist ‘dedicated to the deconstruction of music and its making at a fundamental level, then recreating it in amorphous terms: feeling, landscape, peripheral perception, belonging’ (<a href="https://www.nme.com/reviews/film-reviews/brian-eno-documentary-generative-film-review-3773915" class="web-link">※</a>).</p>

<p><a href="https://www.are.na/block/18973785" class="web-link"><img class="img-padded" src="https://files.justinpickard.net/images/log/2024/08/eno-discreet-music-diagram.jpg" alt="Liner notes to Brian Eno's ‘Discreet Music’ (1975)"></a></p>

<h3 id="interplay-of-archive-database-and-film">Interplay of archive, database, and film</h3>

<p>The interplay of archive, database, and film in ‘Eno’ creates a viewing experience that embodies its subject’s creative philosophy. This performative act of archival exploration, guided by database logic, challenges documentary conventions and the idea of single, fixed historical narrative. The Brain-One software serves as an interface, selecting and arranging database items into a film-like structure, using Eno’s personal video archive as a malleable, generative resource.</p>

<p>Challenging ideas of a ‘definitive’ film, the resulting work aligns with Eno’s own resistance to linear, fixed narratives, including of his own life and work. Interestingly, the film’s generative nature appears to have fostered a unique interview environment. Knowing no single version would be definitive, Eno seems more willing to explore tangents and personal reflections. The resulting interviews serve as a mediating layer, supplying contemporary context for the archival material and guiding viewers’ interpretations without imposing an overly rigid structure.</p>

<p>While the interaction between filmmaker Hustwit and Eno is still present, the film’s structure shifts the primary relationship to that between the viewer and the assembled material. The resulting film offers a contingent view of Eno’s life and work – ‘a scrapbook of scenes from [his] extensive video archives mixed in with footage of Eno in his home studio and garden in rural England, and his scattershot analytical musings on art and life’ (<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/film/article/2024/jul/11/eno-review-roxy-music-brian-eno-high-priest-of-art-tech-experimentalism" class="web-link">※</a>).</p>

<p>The film’s non-linear structure requires active engagement from viewers, who must piece together the story by drawing connections between disparate elements of Eno’s life and work. By inviting viewers to immerse themselves in Eno’s world without the constraints of a rigid storyline, the film opens up alternative forms of knowledge, stressing mood and atmosphere. This approach to memory as a constructive, interpretive process allows viewers to experience Eno’s life as he himself might recall it, offering a nuanced, cumulative representation that a fixed cut could not provide.</p>

<p>‘Eno’ creates a viewing experience that diverges from established documentary formats. By using a generative system to mediate between archival material and new interview footage, the film embodies Eno’s approach to creativity, inviting viewers to engage in a process of meaning-making that mirrors his creative methods. This approach leads us to consider a new concept in documentary filmmaking: <em>procedural empathy</em>, where the <a href="https://justinpickard.net/log/2024/08/21/procedural-portraits-2/" class="web-link">very structure of the film fosters a deeper understanding of its subject</a>.</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Now familiar as a comedian, writer, and host of, among other things, <em>The Great British Bake Off</em>, Danish-British Sandi Toksvig began her TV career in the early 1980s, presenting children’s shows. This appearance interviewing Eno highlights the interconnections between UK media and music during this period, while revealing a lesser-known aspect of her early career. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote web-link" role="doc-backlink">⤴︎</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Paraphrased from Hayles’s ‘<a href="https://www.doi.org/10.3366/ccs.2005.2.2.165" class="web-link">Narrating Bits: Encounters between Humans and Intelligent Machines</a>’ (2005). <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote web-link" role="doc-backlink">⤴︎</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Not least by reviewers, who flagged the role of these ‘<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/film/article/2024/jul/11/eno-review-roxy-music-brian-eno-high-priest-of-art-tech-experimentalism" class="web-link">bleepy, glitchy little interludes</a>’ of ‘<a href="https://www.screendaily.com/reviews/eno-sundance-review/5189591.article" class="web-link">Matrix-like digtal code</a>’ in reminding viewers what, exactly, the film is doing (remaking itself). As Hustwit comments: ‘<a href="https://thequietus.com/culture/film/brian-eno-documentary/" class="web-link">I think you end up appreciating what’s happening more when you’re seeing a little bit of what the system is doing.</a>’ <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote web-link" role="doc-backlink">⤴︎</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Justin Pickard</name></author><category term="authorship" /><category term="creativity" /><category term="archiving" /><category term="databases" /><category term="documentary" /><category term="film" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[[This is the first of a two-part exegesis on ‘Eno’ (2024), a generative documentary about musician and producer Brian Eno. This first post focuses on the documentary’s structure and how it reimagines the relationship between archive, database, and film. In the second part, I’ll show how this structure fosters a ‘procedural empathy’ for its subject, and consider the implications of this approach to documentary filmmaking.]]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dearth</title><link href="https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/06/29/dearth/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dearth" /><published>2024-06-29T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-09-11T14:58:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/06/29/dearth</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/06/29/dearth/"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>When authors use AI-based [creativity support tools] to expand a small amount of input text (such as a one-sentence instruction) to a large amount of output text (such as a complete written story or essay), they delegate many of the creative decisions involved in producing the larger output to the CST — resulting in a piece of writing with an unusually low ratio of human decision-making to output length. In other words, the expressive intent of the author is underspecified relative to the amount of text that is generated, and the resulting piece of writing is unusually sparse in terms of expressive intent per word. We refer to this unusual situation as the <em>dearth of the author</em>: the naïvely AI-augmented author is not absent or dead, but their intent is stretched so thinly over their writing that they may feel barely present.
<cite>— Max Kreminski, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2404.10289" class="web-link">The Dearth of the Author in AI-Supported Writing</a>” (2024)</cite></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>Why post this?</strong> I’m intrigued by how this “dearth of the author” challenges traditional notions of authorship in AI-supported writing. Kreminski’s idea implies a <em>spectrum</em> of authorial presence, which is dialed down as users delegate their decision-making to generative AI tools, snapping to the grid supplied. The concept destabilises binary models of authorship (“either you’re the author or you’re not”), opening new ways to think about creativity and expressive intent.</p>

<p>This “dearth” appears differently across fields. In programming, AI assistance complements existing collaborative workflows, aligning with an emphasis on teamwork and shared resources. Programmers, used to leveraging libraries, frameworks, and pre-written code snippets, may view AI as simply another tool in their arsenal. Writing, however, places a greater premium on individual voice and originality. This emphasis on personal style can create tension with AI-generated text, which struggles to replicate the voice, empathy, and accountability of human-authored writing, resulting in a more noticeable “dearth” of expressive intent.<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote web-link" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p><a href="http://files.justinpickard.net/images/log/2024/06/stream-of-thought.jpg" class="web-link"><img class="img-padded" src="http://files.justinpickard.net/images/log/2024/06/stream-of-thought.jpg" alt="Three-dimensional wavy surface across numbered axis, a grid diagram illustrating the continuity of consciousness, from William James' 'The Principles of Psychology' (1890)."></a></p>

<h4 id="strategies-for-enhancing-authorial-presence"><strong>Strategies for enhancing authorial presence</strong></h4>

<p>Kreminski also speculates about a possible counterpoint to this authorial “dearth”, dubbing such “an abundance of the author.” (Kreminski 2024) But what might this look like in practice? While Kreminski’s concepts address questions of authorship in an age of AI tools, ideas about enhancing authorial presence have historical precedent. The Oulipo movement, founded in 1960, offers an interesting reference point. Oulipian writers used constrained writing techniques to spark creativity and explore new forms of expression. For instance, Georges Perec’s 1969 novel <em>La Disparition</em> was written as a lipogram, entirely excluding the letter ‘e’. Each word choice became a deliberate expressive act, resulting in a text dense with Perec’s creative problem-solving. Rather than limiting expressive intent, such Oulipian constraints served as creative springboards. By forcing writers to find creative solutions within strict parameters, they actually enhanced the author’s unique voice and presence in the text.</p>

<p>While the Oulipo attempted to enhance creativity through structured limitations, the work of writer and media scholar <a href="https://www.kylebooten.me/about.html" class="web-link">Kyle Booten</a> provides a second example of attempts to increase authorial presence, albeit through very different means. Inspired by ancient Greek rhetorical exercises, his “<a href="https://www.kylebooten.me/progym.html" class="web-link">digital progymnasmata</a>” offer real-time feedback, challenging users to refine their language in ways that diverge from expected pattern.<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote web-link" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> For instance, one such tool assesses linguistic rarity, pushing writers to use less common words or syntactic structures. Unlike AI tools that can generate large quantities of text with minimal input, Booten’s tools require writers to actively engage with each new suggestion, combatting authorial dearth by encouraging (if not mandating) more deliberate expressive choices.</p>

<p>I’m particularly taken with his <a href="https://2023.xcoax.org/pdf/booten.pdf" class="web-link">Lotus Chorus Workshop</a>, which takes this concept further, simulating a writing workshop that offers diverse suggestions and critiques after each new sentence. In this writing environment, writers are pushed into a responsive mode, forced to constantly make decisions and assert their creative vision amidst a cacophony of suggestions. This fosters what Booten elsewhere refers to as a “<a href="https://electronicbookreview.com/essay/making-writing-harder-computer-mediated-authorship-and-the-problem-of-care/" class="web-link">Zone of Proximal Derangement</a>”, in which AI suggestions are just strange enough to push writers out of their habitual thought patterns without being completely unusable. By fostering a sense of cognitive overload “that pushes the user’s mind in too many directions at the same time” (Booten 2023), this piece of software aims to stimulate creativity. Setting out to make writing “harder”, it offers a distinct approach to how digital tools might enhance rather than diminish expressive presence in an age of computer-mediated authorship.</p>

<h4 id="prompt-engineering"><strong>Prompt engineering</strong></h4>

<p>In considering techniques to enhance authorial presence, it is also interesting to examine how different groups are making use of current AI writing tools. Although these tools are contributing to this “dearth” of expressive intent by suggesting completions<sup id="fnref:3" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote web-link" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> or generating entire texts, many users are learning sophisticated prompt engineering techniques to produce more targeted, nuanced outputs. “Prompt engineering” can allow users to shape the AI’s output through active, iterative engagement. Creators can steer the AI towards producing content that better reflects their unique perspective and style by providing specific, detailed instructions that include salient contextual factors and desired outcomes.<sup id="fnref:4" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote web-link" rel="footnote">4</a></sup></p>

<p>More complex methods like <a href="https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2201.11903" class="web-link">chain-of-thought prompting</a> can encourage generative models to articulate their intermediate reasoning steps, eliciting more complex and logically structured outputs. Similarly, prompt chaining enables writers to break down complex tasks into smaller, interconnected prompts, each building on the previous response. Such techniques often involve multiple rounds of refinement, with users crafting prompts that specify salient contextual factors, desired outcomes, and even the reasoning process itself. This can allow for finer-grained control over the creative process, producing outputs that better align with users’ own perspectives and expressive intents.</p>

<p><a href="http://files.justinpickard.net/images/log/2024/06/the-author-depositing-his-voice.jpg" class="web-link"><img class="img-padded" src="http://files.justinpickard.net/images/log/2024/06/the-author-depositing-his-voice.jpg" alt="Black and white illustration from Octave Uzanne's 'The End of Books' (1894). Two men at a patent office desk, one speaking into a large horn-like device. Caption reads: 'The Author Depositing his Voice at the Patent-Office, to Prevent Counterfeiting.'"></a></p>

<h4 id="future-directions-for-computer-mediated-authorship"><strong>Future directions for computer-mediated authorship</strong></h4>

<p>AI writing tools have the potential to enhance authorial presence by encouraging more intentional and distinctive writing. Inspired by Booten and the Oulipo, future such tools could be designed to promote revision, increase linguistic density, and foster deeper engagement with the creative process. By asking probing questions, suggesting areas for expansion, and providing real-time feedback, they could help writers refine their ideas and expression over multiple drafts, strengthening their voice and presence in the text. As these tools evolve, they may reconfigure many of our assumptions about authorship. Rather than viewing AI as a threat to authorial presence, we could come to position it as a collaborator in new forms of augmented creativity.</p>

<p>From Oulipian constraints to the cognitive challenges posed by Booten’s digital progymnasmata, and the nuances of prompt engineering, we see various attempts to reassert human agency and intentionality in the creative process. The greater adoption and integration of generative AI tools could lead to a redefinition of authorship that emphasises the curation, direction, and refinement of content, rather than the methodological individualism of singular visions and distinctive voices. I’m particularly interested in the potential for collaborative models where <em>multiple</em> human authors work alongside AI systems.</p>

<p>Imagine a writing environment where a team of authors, each with their own unique perspectives, engages with a generative AI system that acts as mediator and creative catalyst. This more collaborative approach could lead to rich, multifaceted texts that blend diverse human perspectives with AI-enhanced creativity. AI systems could act as a mediator, identifying connections between authors’ ideas and proposing novel combinations. It might also help manage the workflow, ensuring that each contributor’s voice is heard and integrated. Beyond creative writing, a “writers room” model could be valuable in fields requiring interdisciplinary collaboration, such as policy development or academic research.</p>

<p>However, as we explore these new possibilities, we must remain mindful of the challenges. The integration of AI in collaborative writing processes might inadvertently homogenise writing styles or lead to an over-reliance on AI-suggested connections. It could also raise questions about attribution, ownership, and control. How do we acknowledge the role of AI in such collaborative works? How might different configurations of human-AI collaboration affect the power structures within writing teams? These are complex issues that will require ongoing dialogue and experimentation.</p>

<p>Ultimately, the goal is not to let the “dearth of the author” force us into a defensive crouch, but to imagine and cultivate rich, collaborative spaces where human creativity and AI capabilities can coexist and interact. By embracing the potential of AI-augmented writing while engaging with its implications, we can create the conditions for these tools to scaffold an abundance of expressive intent, rather than resulting in its dearth.</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Consider the use of personal anecdotes in longform essays, a highly-valued feature in human-authored texts, but challenging for AI to replicate; this ability to weave personal experiences into a narrative is a clear example of strong authorial presence. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote web-link" role="doc-backlink">⤴︎</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>I am grateful to Nick Seaver for introducing me to Booten’s work. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote web-link" role="doc-backlink">⤴︎</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Compare with the phrase “spicy autocomplete”; a colloquial, somewhat pejorative label, casting new generative AI technologies as more sophisticated versions of existing (and, by now, <em>familiar</em>) text prediction tools. <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote web-link" role="doc-backlink">⤴︎</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Mark Carrigan discusses <a href="https://markcarrigan.net/2024/05/17/prompt-engineering-is-an-expression-of-cultural-capital/" class="web-link">prompt engineering as an expression of cultural capital</a>. Those with broader cultural knowledge or more diverse experiences, Carrigan argues, might be better at crafting and framing prompts, thereby benefitting from stronger, more expressive outputs. <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote web-link" role="doc-backlink">⤴︎</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Justin Pickard</name></author><category term="quotes" /><category term="genai" /><category term="authorship" /><category term="creativity" /><category term="tools" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[When authors use AI-based [creativity support tools] to expand a small amount of input text (such as a one-sentence instruction) to a large amount of output text (such as a complete written story or essay), they delegate many of the creative decisions involved in producing the larger output to the CST — resulting in a piece of writing with an unusually low ratio of human decision-making to output length. In other words, the expressive intent of the author is underspecified relative to the amount of text that is generated, and the resulting piece of writing is unusually sparse in terms of expressive intent per word. We refer to this unusual situation as the dearth of the author: the naïvely AI-augmented author is not absent or dead, but their intent is stretched so thinly over their writing that they may feel barely present. — Max Kreminski, “The Dearth of the Author in AI-Supported Writing” (2024)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Logical piano: 2024-W25</title><link href="https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/06/23/logical-piano/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Logical piano: 2024-W25" /><published>2024-06-23T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-09-11T14:58:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/06/23/logical-piano</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/06/23/logical-piano/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="solstitial-reflections-on-boolean-logic-divination-and-ritual-machines">Solstitial reflections on Boolean logic, divination, and ritual machines.</h4>

<h5 id="undertakings"><strong>Undertakings:</strong></h5>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Ritual machines:</strong> Another week, another art application deadline. Teamed up with two remote collaborators for a sprint to meet a commission exploring the intersection of AI and ritual practices. Coordinating across time zones and platforms (Miro boards, web docs, WhatsApp, etc.) posed its own challenges, and we ended up working in a kind of threaded relay, breaking only for dinner and a walk around the block to pet some neighbourhood cats. Don’t know what our chances are, but I’m content that we submitted a convincing proposal, and enjoyed the process.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Static site:</strong> Spent most of Tuesday on the ongoing website redesign. I’m doubling down on <a href="https://rsms.me/inter/" class="web-link">Inter</a> as a primary typeface, but have tweaked some of its <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_typographic_features#OpenType_typographic_features" class="web-link">OpenType features</a> to make it more distinctive. Also added some drop shadows to block quotes, to separate them from the surrounding text, and fiddled around with my use of tables. It’s been a relief to make a clean break with WordPress, even as grappling with CSS and typeface weights has felt, at times, like squinting my way through an optometry appointment (“<em>Option A</em>, or … <em>Option B?</em>”).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Re/imagining technology:</strong> Set aside a couple of days to work on FoAM’s “<a href="https://fo.am/activities/anarchive/" class="web-link">Anarchive</a>”, getting stuck into our latest multi-author reader, “Re/imagining technology”. I’ve been trying to recontextualise some work from the early 2000s for a contemporary audience, tacking between past insights and future possibilities. From midweek, I shifted from editing to starting work on my own contributions; figuring out the parameters for a planned text sketching one possible scenario for the (near-)future of remote collaboration.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Querent.py:</strong> Completed an initial prototype of this tarot-reading programme I’ve been working on, a significant early milestone in my Python journey. Inspired by, and striving to reconcile, the works of Ian Bogost and Alejandro Jodorowsky<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote web-link" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, this undertaking devoured a not-insubstantial chunk of the past fortnight. A central early challenge came in roughing out a data structure flexible enough to capture the tarot’s associative symbolism, with the EAV model emerging as an <a href="https://github.com/timcowlishaw/enxaneta/blob/main/documentation/working_notes/02_eav-data-model.md" class="web-link">unexpectedly promising approach</a>, despite its mixed reputation.<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote web-link" rel="footnote">2</a></sup></p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://files.justinpickard.net/images/log/2024/06/querent-py-prototype.jpg" class="web-link"><img class="img-padded" src="http://files.justinpickard.net/images/log/2024/06/querent-py-prototype.jpg" alt="Querent.py prototype, June 2024"></a></p>

<h5 id="side-missions"><strong>Side-missions:</strong></h5>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The log-compost continuum:</strong> Published a log entry on <a href="https://justinpickard.net/log/2024/06/17/barefoot-and-malleable/" class="web-link">barefoot coders and malleable software</a>, bridging my recent Python misadventures and longer-standing interests in improvisation and appropriate technology. I’m trying to get back into the habit of writing and publishing on the web, something that seems to involve figuring out what qualifies as a sufficiently “loggable” line of thought. At a structural level, I’m also trying to get greater clarity on the relationship between my website’s log, as a <a href="https://justinpickard.net/log/2023/04/20/binnacle/" class="web-link">chronological record of discrete observations</a>, and this new “<a href="https://justinpickard.net/compost/" class="web-link">Compost</a>” digital garden, a <a href="https://maggieappleton.com/garden-history" class="web-link">mulch</a> of interconnected hunches and notes-to-self; slow, rhizomatic, and iteratively refined.<sup id="fnref:3" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote web-link" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> The next step is to improve these notes’ navigability, unpicking the assumptions and operational logics of backlinks and the network graph format. I’m aiming to maintain this as a living, breathing knowledge base, running alongside (and underneath) the rest of my site.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Excavating ELIZA:</strong> As part of “Enexata,” mine and <a href="https://www.timcowlishaw.co.uk/" class="web-link">Tim’s</a> “<a href="https://github.com/timcowlishaw/enxaneta" class="web-link">sprawling mutual aid skill exchange</a>” (his words), I’ve forked a <a href="https://github.com/wadetb/eliza" class="web-link">Python emulation of ELIZA</a>, the pioneering chatbot developed by Joseph Weizenbaum at MIT in the 1960s. To better understand ELIZA’s inner workings, I’ve started annotating the Python codebase. I’m treating this exercise as a form of experimental media archaeology, hunting for traces of the programme’s original social and cultural contexts, while considering how its architecture might be repurposed for contemporary conversational interfaces. Alongside this ELIZA side-mission, I also made some headway on (though didn’t finish) <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/01622439241245746" class="web-link">this article</a> on “ugly code” at Russian search engine firm Yandex. Sitting at the juncture of <a href="https://justinpickard.net/compost/valuation/" class="web-link">valuation studies</a> and <a href="https://justinpickard.net/compost/critical-technical-practice/" class="web-link">critical technical practice</a>, the article examines how aesthetic judgments and values shape software development. Aiming to discuss these themes with Tim next week, exploring how they might shape the next stages of our work together.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Taming complexity:</strong> This week, I’ve been grappling with the challenge of instilling some kind of order on a firehose of ideas, particularly for the multi-author reader I’m working on with FoAM. Enter “<a href="https://github.com/ycnmhd/obsidian-lineage" class="web-link">Lineage</a>”, an Obsidian plugin approximating much of the functionality of <a href="https://gingkowriter.com/" class="web-link">Gingko Writer</a>.<sup id="fnref:4" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote web-link" rel="footnote">4</a></sup> As I understand it, the plugin adds a layer of invisible HTML comment “breaks” to markdown files, visually interpreting these as “cards” that can then be hierarchically organised with parent/child dependencies. I’m still experimenting, but the multi-column, drag-and-drop interface could be a game-changer; dramatically reducing the friction in outlining complex texts.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Huff-duff:</strong> A standing call with <a href="https://andrewlb.com/" class="web-link">Andrew L-B</a> yielded some reflection on professional legibility in an increasingly fragmented digital landscape. In a <a href="https://andrewlb.com/blog/legible-work" class="web-link">blog post</a> this week, he draws an analogy between WWII-era <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/High-frequency_direction_finding" class="web-link">high-frequency direction finding</a> (HF/DF or “huff-duff”) and the information asymmetries inherent to the challenge of building (assembling?) a career. Like a submarine, he argues, we “transmit” our skills and contributions, hoping to be “detected” by allies and would-be collaborators. But this analogy raises some tricky questions: constant transmission can be exhausting, and risks reducing us to a narrow, distorted slice of our capabilities. This challenge is being compounded by the erosion of mass-userbase social media platforms, with our “transmissions” fragmented across digital spaces. Perhaps the goal isn’t to be a perfectly detectable submarine, but to cultivate a network of trusted huff-duff stations: allies, mentors, and collaborators who can appreciate our evolving mix of skills; helping us navigate, even as we change course.<sup id="fnref:5" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote web-link" rel="footnote">5</a></sup> (<a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/9780262581462/cognition-in-the-wild/" class="web-link">※</a>)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Boolean loops:</strong> Found myself stuck in an unexpected flow state late Friday night, plumbing a speculative rabbit hole with the <a href="https://www.anthropic.com/news/claude-3-5-sonnet" class="web-link">newly-launched Claude language model</a>. Sparked by a passing reference in a <a href="https://harpers.org/archive/2024/07/the-gods-of-logic-benjamin-labatut-ai/" class="web-link">Benjamin Labateut essay</a>, this, combined with a familiarity with “bools” from my recent Python noodlings, led me to enlist Claude in working through the implications of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Boole" class="web-link">George Boole</a>, father of Boolean logic, surviving an 1864 bout of pneumonia and living into the 1880s. The model’s speculations ranged from the plausible (earlier applications of probability theory in actuarial contexts, more reliable telephone networks) to the offbeat (“True/False cutlery sets”, Boolean gardening, a proliferation of <a href="https://computerhistory.org/blog/logical-piano-lessons/" class="web-link">logical pianos</a>). As someone who’s been drawn to <a href="/compost/counterfactual-reasoning" class="web-link">counterfactuals</a> since my teenage years, I’m now starting to think about more structured approaches to these machine-assisted thought experiments. And while I’m not yet sure what form this might take, there’s definitely something interesting here.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/801529" class="web-link"><img class="img-padded" src="http://files.justinpickard.net/images/log/2024/06/jevons-logical-machine.jpg" alt="William Henry Jevons' logical piano"></a></p>

<h5 id="next-week"><strong>Next week:</strong></h5>

<ul>
  <li>Preparing the ground to pivot to phase two of this Python-ethnography collaboration with Tim, having just nerd-sniped him into bootstrapping <a href="https://github.com/timcowlishaw/humus" class="web-link">Humus</a>, a permacomputing-aligned “composting database.”<sup id="fnref:6" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:6" class="footnote web-link" rel="footnote">6</a></sup>
</li>
  <li>Then to London Monday afternoon, where I’m catsitting while D’s sister and her fiancé brave predicted rain (?) at Glastonbury. I’ll be volunteering at the <a href="https://therai.org.uk/conferences/anthropology-and-education" class="web-link">RAI Anthropology &amp; Education conference</a>, lured in by a run of sessions on how generative AI is starting to sluice into anthropology education and ethnographic methods.</li>
  <li>Catching up with friends and colleagues while in London.</li>
  <li><del>Likely capping the week with a day at the <a href="https://folklore-society.com/event/digital-folklore-conference/" class="web-link">Digital Folklore conference</a>, before heading back up to York.</del></li>
</ul>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>In short: hewing closely to <a href="https://purple.fr/magazine/fw-2009-issue-12/psychomagic-alejandro-jodorowsky/" class="web-link">Jodorowsky’s approach to the tarot</a>, while treating the exercise as a work of <a href="https://justinpickard.net/compost/bogostian-carpentry/" class="web-link">Bogostian carpentry</a>. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote web-link" role="doc-backlink">⤴︎</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Often seen as a last resort due to their complexity, and potential performance issues, EAV structures persist in domains like medical databases where the need to accommodate evolving, heterogeneous data beats any concerns about efficiency; engaging with this tension has helped me start to bend my head around the trade-offs inherent to data modelling. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote web-link" role="doc-backlink">⤴︎</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Tom’s been <a href="https://tmsullivan.co.uk/information-cultivation-1-%E2%80%94-principles" class="web-link">thinking along similar lines</a> this past week: “The point of information cultivation is to liquify productivity, turning it into a portable way of thinking which filters into how you use different tools”. <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote web-link" role="doc-backlink">⤴︎</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>A tool I’ve long admired, but struggled to integrate into my workflow. <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote web-link" role="doc-backlink">⤴︎</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:5" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>This networked approach riffs on Herminia Ibarra’s <em><a href="https://herminiaibarra.com/working-identity-book/" class="web-link">Working Identity</a></em>, which goes hard on the importance of experimenting with new activities and expanding our circles as our careers progress. <a href="#fnref:5" class="reversefootnote web-link" role="doc-backlink">⤴︎</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:6" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>No, I don’t know either. <a href="#fnref:6" class="reversefootnote web-link" role="doc-backlink">⤴︎</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Justin Pickard</name></author><category term="weeknotes" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Solstitial reflections on Boolean logic, divination, and ritual machines.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Barefoot and malleable</title><link href="https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/06/17/barefoot-and-malleable/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Barefoot and malleable" /><published>2024-06-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-09-11T14:58:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/06/17/barefoot-and-malleable</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/06/17/barefoot-and-malleable/"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>‘Barefoot developers are going to be people who live in this middle bit. At the moment, these are people like the teachers who make elaborate Notion spreadsheets for managing classes. Or students who make over-the-top personal dashboards. Or financial planning wonks producing extensive spreadsheets. They are people who are technically savvy and interested in solving problems for themselves and people around them, but don’t want to become fully-fledged programmers. They still live within the world of end-user-facing applications. At the moment, they rely on low and no-code tools. And they do wildly complex things within them, pushing these apps to their limits. They are the kinds of people who would be thrilled to have more agency and power over computers.’
<cite>— Maggie Appleton, “<a href="https://maggieappleton.com/home-cooked-software" class="web-link">Home-Cooked Software and Barefoot Developers</a>” (2024)</cite></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>‘A joke that comes up often among AI-skeptical programmers goes something like this: “Great, now no one will have to write code, they’ll only have to write exact, precise specifications of computer behavior…” (implied: oh wait, that is code!) I suspect we’ll look back on this view as short-sighted. LLMs can iteratively work with users and ask them questions to develop their specifications, and can also fill in underspecified details using common sense. This doesn’t mean those are trivial challenges, but I expect to see progress on those fronts.’
<cite>— Geoffrey Litt, “<a href="https://www.geoffreylitt.com/2023/03/25/llm-end-user-programming" class="web-link">Malleable Software in the Age of LLMs</a>” (2023)</cite></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>Why post this?</strong> At the time of posting, I’m about a fortnight into full-tilt, LLM-supported Python-wrangling, coming from a standing start, as part of this <a href="https://github.com/timcowlishaw/enxaneta" class="web-link">skill exchange with Tim</a>. Appleton’s talk neatly threads the needle between my newfound software side-missions and existing interests in improvisation and <a href="/compost/appropriate-technology/" class="web-link">appropriate technology</a>; an overlap I’d begun exploring, tentatively, through the lens of <a href="/compost/situated-software/" class="web-link">situated software</a> (also one of Appleton’s reference points).</p>

<p>Looking ahead, and with an ethnographic hat on, I’m interested in the motives and values of these “barefoot developers”, and how they differ from those of pro software devs. How do principles of <a href="/compost/tinkering/" class="web-link">tinkering</a> and <a href="/compost/bricolage/" class="web-link">bricolage</a> map to these new ways of building (brewing?) software? Can these new generative technologies support those trying to root their tools in local contexts and needs?</p>

<p>And: What new communities and practices might form around “barefoot programming”? Will they track or diverge from existing open source cultures? How will barefoot developers’ outputs be framed and judged? Are we looking at a steeper hierarchy or blurred boundaries? How might this reshape insider/outsider power dynamics and participation in software and technology?</p>]]></content><author><name>Justin Pickard</name></author><category term="quotes" /><category term="computational thinking" /><category term="genai" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[‘Barefoot developers are going to be people who live in this middle bit. At the moment, these are people like the teachers who make elaborate Notion spreadsheets for managing classes. Or students who make over-the-top personal dashboards. Or financial planning wonks producing extensive spreadsheets. They are people who are technically savvy and interested in solving problems for themselves and people around them, but don’t want to become fully-fledged programmers. They still live within the world of end-user-facing applications. At the moment, they rely on low and no-code tools. And they do wildly complex things within them, pushing these apps to their limits. They are the kinds of people who would be thrilled to have more agency and power over computers.’ — Maggie Appleton, “Home-Cooked Software and Barefoot Developers” (2024)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Countless openings</title><link href="https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/06/09/countless-openings/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Countless openings" /><published>2024-06-09T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-09-11T14:58:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/06/09/countless-openings</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/06/09/countless-openings/"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>‘[Literary culture] is a machine of great complexity, containing people, books and institutions, fed by the voices of the dead, but also by bread and cheese, and venting language into the world through countless openings. Such a machine has always been combinatorial and always producing great work as much by accident as intent.’
<cite>— James Vincent, “<a href="https://www.faber.co.uk/journal/do-chatbots-dream-of-ai-poetry-calvino-madness-and-machine-literature/" class="web-link">Do Chatbots Dream of AI Poetry?</a>” (2024)</cite></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>Why post this?</strong> Struck by Vincent’s perspective on these generative models’ <em>continuities</em> with existing literary culture, rather than treating them as a rupture or radical departure.</p>]]></content><author><name>Justin Pickard</name></author><category term="quotes" /><category term="combinatorics" /><category term="genai" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[‘[Literary culture] is a machine of great complexity, containing people, books and institutions, fed by the voices of the dead, but also by bread and cheese, and venting language into the world through countless openings. Such a machine has always been combinatorial and always producing great work as much by accident as intent.’ — James Vincent, “Do Chatbots Dream of AI Poetry?” (2024)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Deep play: 2024-W21</title><link href="https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/05/25/deep-play/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Deep play: 2024-W21" /><published>2024-05-25T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-09-11T14:58:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/05/25/deep-play</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/05/25/deep-play/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="residency-application-coastal-birdwatching-flow-charts-and-an-unexpected-detour-into-16th-century-martial-arts">Residency application, coastal birdwatching, flow charts, and an unexpected detour into 16th-century martial arts.</h4>

<h5 id="undertakings"><strong>Undertakings:</strong></h5>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Residency application:</strong> Spent the weekend racing to clarify and complete supporting materials for an artist residency application. Crafting a team proposal with a lead resident, we had to be clear and concrete about our plans and interests, strategising about how best to meet a stringent word limit. We submitted just before the deadline, at midnight on Sunday.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Thick description:</strong> Stayed up late to read Clifford Geertz’s ‘<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/20028014" class="web-link">Deep Play: Notes on the Balinese cockfight</a>’, which I had assigned Tim as an introduction to thick description.<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote web-link" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> Halfway through, I realised I’d never read the entire thing myself, having skipped some key theory modules during an undergraduate joint honours.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Exnaneta:</strong> I also worked through some new tutorial materials Tim uploaded to GitHub, using increasingly tortured kitchen analogies to bend my head around some key programming terms (how is a function like a rice-cooker, etc.). Took me a little too long on Friday afternoon to realise the Raspberry Pi <em>was</em>, in fact, working, despite its green light not staying on.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Too many flow charts:</strong> Earlier in the week, I followed David’s recommendation to explore <a href="https://mermaid.js.org/" class="web-link">Mermaid</a> diagrams, working up a version of this convoluted custom task management system I’ve been tinkering with since December (see below). This morning, I followed up by generating a <a href="https://github.com/timcowlishaw/enxaneta/blob/main/documentation/diagrams/overview.md" class="web-link">ludicrous flowchart</a> outlining the rough plan for mine and Tim’s planned skill exchange.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://files.justinpickard.net/images/log/2024/05/Custom-task-statuses.svg" class="web-link"><img class="img-padded" src="https://files.justinpickard.net/images/log/2024/05/Custom-task-statuses.svg" alt="Custom Task Statuses"></a></p>

<h5 id="side-missions"><strong>Side-missions:</strong></h5>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Puffin hunt:</strong> Spent an extended weekend with D and my parents in the North York Moors, including day trips to Scarborough and the mist-shrouded Bempton Cliffs, where my choice of shorts proved wholly inadequate. Listening to a volley of voice notes from a friend while losing feeling in my fingers, as the rest of our party gazed hopefully over the North Sea, I eventually had to go and wait in the car. Lots of guillemots, fulmars, etc. Everyone except me saw a puffin.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Web development:</strong> Building on last week’s efforts, I tweaked and honed the <a href="https://justinpickard.net/compost/" class="web-link">knowledge graph</a> and started populating my <a href="https://justinpickard.net/compost/about/" class="web-link">metaphorical compost heap</a> with rough notes and placeholder content. Having added a ‘last updated’ timestamp to most pages, I’m now grappling with the challenge of rendering my (lengthy, somewhat shaggy) CV in a way that will be intelligible to the casual visitor.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Many Knightly Exercises:</strong> Robustly nerd-sniped by a schoolfriend’s brother, a historical European martial arts enthusiast, who reached out for help using machine translation on a 16th-century Bolognese fencing manual.<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote web-link" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> Grappling with the problem consumed my Thursday morning, as I scoped options for piping the source text into an API vs. his locally hosting an open source machine translation tool. Might have promised him a text-chunking script.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://files.justinpickard.net/images/log/2024/05/Ghisliero.jpg" class="web-link"><img class="img-padded" src="https://files.justinpickard.net/images/log/2024/05/Ghisliero.jpg" alt="Ghisliero"></a></p>

<ul>
  <li>
<strong>Forkable architectures:</strong> Actual full-blown phone call with co-conspirator <a href="https://no2self.net/" class="web-link">Rob</a> on Friday night, after our efforts to connect over video were foiled by limited bandwidth. It was good to catch up; we talked about architectural education, versioning and forkability, the aftermath of this month’s West Midlands mayoral election, and lock-in and obduracy in Birmingham’s housing sector.</li>
</ul>

<h5 id="next-week"><strong>Next week:</strong></h5>

<ul>
  <li>Back into the Anarchive trenches from Monday to wrestle with the next set of texts, on <a href="https://fo.am/silver-route/" class="web-link">alternative visions for technology</a>.</li>
  <li>Volunteer call on Tuesday as initial prep for the Royal Anthropological Institute’s <a href="https://therai.org.uk/conferences/anthropology-and-education" class="web-link">Anthropology &amp; Education conference</a> in London at the end of June.</li>
  <li>Sitting in on a talk by <a href="https://lu.ma/1qkmdsfp?tk=xE1raJ" class="web-link">David</a> on Thursday, as part of AIxDesign’s research on ‘<a href="https://nadiapiet.notion.site/Esoteric-AI-Public-6eca55b6ea3e4e20a3e3537ffc2a026c" class="web-link">Esoteric AI</a>’; which is increasingly relevant to some ideas I’m exploring.</li>
</ul>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Thick description goes beyond simple observation to interpret the meanings and symbols embedded in social actions. A cornerstone of contemporary ethnography, this approach underscores the importance of viewing cultures not as static entities to be dissected and categorised, but dynamic webs of significance, constructed and negotiated by individuals in their everyday lives. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote web-link" role="doc-backlink">⤴︎</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Captain Federico Ghisliero’s <em>Rules of Many Knightly Exercises</em>, published in Parma in 1587. Ghisliero was a Bolognese soldier, whose treatise, one of the earliest on the rapier, is notable for its use of geometry. Illustrations showing sequences of movement were added later, and vary between the few surviving copies. Mike’s translation in-progress is available <a href="https://msmallridge.wordpress.com/2023/08/03/ghisliero-translation/" class="web-link">here</a>. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote web-link" role="doc-backlink">⤴︎</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Justin Pickard</name></author><category term="weeknotes" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Residency application, coastal birdwatching, flow charts, and an unexpected detour into 16th-century martial arts.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Engrossed: 2024-W20</title><link href="https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/05/17/engrossed/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Engrossed: 2024-W20" /><published>2024-05-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-09-11T14:58:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/05/17/engrossed</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/05/17/engrossed/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="found-myself-in-a-machine-facilitated-fugue-this-week-head-down-puzzling-my-way-through-new-technical-and-conceptual-terrain-with-a-few-video-calls-anchoring-me-to-a-shared-social-reality">Found myself in a machine-facilitated fugue this week; head-down, puzzling my way through new (technical and conceptual) terrain, with a few video calls anchoring me to a shared social reality.</h4>

<h5 id="undertakings"><strong>Undertakings:</strong></h5>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Web development:</strong> A frankly inadvisible amount of website-wrangling throughout this week, including some late-night rabbit-holes and debugging loops. I’m now most of the way through an LLM-supported rebuild, shifting my site away from Wordpress to a Jekyll static site. With outside machine support, I’ve been getting more comfortable with working in the command line, Visual Studio Code, etc., and have successfully implemented wiki-style linking, tagging, and a backlinking system, and got a rudimentary vis.js knowledge graph up and running.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Latent Intimacies:</strong> Check-in with <a href="https://vjnks.com/" class="web-link">Vytas</a> on Tuesday evening, synchronising our thinking about how to develop some of the outcomes of the “Synthetic Minds” collaborative prototyping residency we were part of back in January-February; also helped him think through some text for an (unrelated) publication later in the week.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Choreographing attention:</strong> IM meeting with M (dialling in from a electric vehicle charging station somewhere in Croatia), postponed after I spread myself a bit too thinly last week; talked through plans for getting stuck into the next <a href="https://fo.am/activities/anarchive/" class="web-link">Anarchive</a> Reader, committing to a focused two-week editorial sprint from the 27th, as something preferable to a more thinly-spread, piecemeal approach.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Enxaneta:</strong> Week twoish of a planned six-month Python-for-ethnography collaborative skill exchange with <a href="https://www.timcowlishaw.co.uk/" class="web-link">Tim</a>; reflecting on some on my website-wrangling experiences, and the outcomes of a <a href="https://github.com/timcowlishaw/enxaneta/blob/main/documentation/ethnography/01_ethnographic-observation.md" class="web-link">field observation exercise</a> I’d set. We talked a bit about critical technical practice, Britishness abroad, Mariann Vaczi’s monograph <em>Catalonia’s Human Towers</em>, and different approaches to bounding and specifying ethnographic fieldsites, and set some next steps for the coming weeks.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://files.justinpickard.net/images/log/2024/05/Tim-habia-dithered.png" class="web-link"><img class="img-padded" src="https://files.justinpickard.net/images/log/2024/05/Tim-habia-dithered.png" alt="Tim, Habia etc., dithere"></a></p>

<h5 id="side-missions"><strong>Side-missions:</strong></h5>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Dowsing</strong>: Caught an afternoon screening of <em><a href="https://www.inverse.com/entertainment/la-chimera-review-digital-release" class="web-link">La Chimera</a></em> with D over the weekend, which was shaggy and weird, with a dreamy energy that seeped into the rest of the week. Now imagining a dowsing-specific double feature, running it alongside Ben Wheatley’s <em>A Field in England</em>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Thick presents:</strong> Social catch-up with <a href="https://www.richardsandford.net/about/" class="web-link">Richard</a>, having been in close contact during a flurry of activity putting together an (unsuccessful) funding proposal for a small project on ecological citizenship earlier in the year; we’re both going to be at <a href="https://anticipationconference.org/" class="web-link">Anticipation</a> in September, so useful to get a sense of the kinds of things he’s thinking about (<a href="https://www.richardsandford.net/2024/04/24/thick-present-in-trento/" class="web-link">※</a>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The jagged frontier:</strong> Monthly Friday morning call with <a href="https://andrewlb.com/" class="web-link">Andrew</a>, a little unfocused after staying up into the early hours wrestling with GitHub branches<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote web-link" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>; a wide-ranging chat, covering Wardley maps of dog-breeding as a service, generative AI’s <a href="https://www.hbs.edu/faculty/Pages/item.aspx?num=64700" class="web-link">jagged frontier</a>, the <em>Tao of Pooh</em>, and the ‘protocolisation of small team collaboration’ (whatever that means).</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h5 id="next-week"><strong>Next week:</strong></h5>

<ul>
  <li>Shift from technical web development to tweaking the site’s look and feel, and thinking about content strategy.</li>
  <li>Another skill exchange session with Tim, going deeper on participant observation and fieldnotes.</li>
  <li>Editing work, sketching some ‘serving suggestions’ for a deconstructed photo book.</li>
  <li>Call about an archiving/experimental publishing side-mission.</li>
</ul>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Don’t talk to me about GitHub branches. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote web-link" role="doc-backlink">⤴︎</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Justin Pickard</name></author><category term="weeknotes" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Found myself in a machine-facilitated fugue this week; head-down, puzzling my way through new (technical and conceptual) terrain, with a few video calls anchoring me to a shared social reality.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Choices about what is salient</title><link href="https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/01/06/choices-about-what-is-salient/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Choices about what is salient" /><published>2024-01-06T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2024-09-11T14:58:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/01/06/choices-about-what-is-salient</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/01/06/choices-about-what-is-salient/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="a-couple-of-paragraphs-from-the-phd-thesis-unravelling-context-having-drawn-too-close-to-the-large-language-model-and-been-spaghettified">A couple of paragraphs from the <a href="../../../../../phd" class="web-link">PhD thesis</a>, unravelling context, having drawn too close to the <a href="http://ai.stanford.edu/blog/understanding-incontext/" class="web-link">large language model</a> and been <a href="https://science.nasa.gov/universe/what-happens-when-something-gets-too-close-to-a-black-hole/" class="web-link">spaghettified</a>.</h4>

<blockquote>
  <p>Context often appears as an explanatory staple and normative imperative; a self-evident, black-boxed set of ‘external circumstances’ to which objects must yield (Woolgar and Lezaun, 2013). In his writings on context-aware computing, Paul Dourish takes a different approach, differentiating between <em>representational</em> and <em>interactional</em> interpretations of context (Dourish, 2004). In representational accounts, context denotes the features of a given setting. For interactionalists, however, context is something people <em>do</em>; a localised achievement, with tangible material effects, actively produced through social practice (Seaver, 2015: 1105; Asdal and Moser, 2012: 294; Dourish, 2004: 22). Where calls to contextualise typically assume issues and objects are separate from their surroundings, ‘establishing context’ is a <em>political</em> project, bound up with questions of method and practice (Seaver, 2015: 1106). Since, for interactionalists, context is not self-evident, any analysis of the boundaries between context and content entails choices about what is salient, and ‘where the work of contextualization should cease.’ (ibid.)</p>

  <p>For anthropologists, an early emphasis on holism and local field sites has, in recent decades, yielded to a relational understanding of context as comprising a ‘set of <em>connections</em> between the object of inquiry and its surroundings.’ (Morita, 2014: 215) As anthropologist Nick Seaver observes, while ‘it is common sense that to put things <em>in context</em> is good and to take them out of context is <em>bad</em>’, this has often overshadowed disagreements over what, exactly, context <em>is</em> (Seaver, 2015: 1105). At the same time, much work in STS has been shaped by an imperative to avoid either explaining science by its own internal logic or reducing it to a function of its social environments (cf. Asdal and Moser, 2012). In both fields, a once-common explanatory recourse to context has faltered, finding ‘nothing “beyond” [or outside] with which to explain something else.’ (ibid: 295)</p>
</blockquote>

<hr>

<h4 id="readings">Readings</h4>

<p>Asdal, K., &amp; Moser, I. (2012). Experiments in context and contexting. <em>Science, Technology, &amp; Human Values</em>, 37(4), 291–306. 🔒<a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00779-003-0253-8" class="web-link">https://doi.org/10.1177/0162243912449749</a></p>

<p>Dourish, P. (2004). What we talk about when we talk about context. <em>Personal and Ubiquitous Computing</em>, 8(1), 19–30. 🔒<a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00779-003-0253-8" class="web-link">https://doi.org/10.1007/s00779-003-0253-8</a></p>

<p>Fabian, J. (1995). Ethnographic misunderstanding and the perils of context. <em>American Anthropologist</em>, 97(1), 41–50. 🔒<a href="https://doi.org/10.1525/aa.1995.97.1.02a00080" class="web-link">https://doi.org/10.1525/aa.1995.97.1.02a00080</a></p>

<p>Law, J., &amp; Moser, I. (2012). Contexts and culling. <em>Science, Technology, &amp; Human Values</em>, 37(4), 332–354. 🔒<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0162243911425055" class="web-link">https://doi.org/10.1177/0162243911425055</a></p>

<p>Morita, A. (2014). The ethnographic machine: Experimenting with context and comparison in Strathernian ethnography. <em>Science, Technology, &amp; Human Values</em>, 39(2), 214–235. 🔒<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0162243913503189" class="web-link">https://doi.org/10.1177/0162243913503189</a></p>

<p>Seaver, N. (2015). The nice thing about context is that everyone has it. <em>Media, Culture &amp; Society</em>, 37(7), 1101–1109. 🔒<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0163443715594102" class="web-link">https://doi.org/10.1177/0163443715594102</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Justin Pickard</name></author><category term="context" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A couple of paragraphs from the PhD thesis, unravelling context, having drawn too close to the large language model and been spaghettified.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Binnacle</title><link href="https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2023/04/20/binnacle/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Binnacle" /><published>2023-04-20T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-09-11T14:58:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2023/04/20/binnacle</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2023/04/20/binnacle/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="to-stain-the-blank-page-on-blogging-and-the-ships-log-through-the-figure-of-the-binnacle">To stain the blank page: on blogging and the ship’s log, through the figure of the binnacle.</h4>

<p>What is it to <del>start</del> resume blogging now, in the spring of 2023? (Other than it no longer being 1998, that is.) It seems uncertainty is the order of the day. Some speak of a “<a href="https://www.unpopularfront.news/p/have-you-heard-about-the-polycrisis" class="web-link">polycrisis</a>”, while bracing for further ruptures amid mounting turbulence. The digital leviathans founder, the public sphere takes damage, giving way to a froth of invite-only backchannels and social dark pools. Early ripples, perhaps, of <a href="https://www.are.na/justin-pickard/epistemic-breakdown" class="web-link">epistemic breakdown</a>; a peeling-apart of our criteria for appraising truth amid information overload, new synthetic media, and a multiply-breached social contract.</p>

<p>Today, the web is no longer new media, but the backdrop, staging, and atmospherics of lives lived online. Blog is a clipping of a kenning, hinging the network and the archive. And if the novelty of the web is fast-fading, then we should be places more stress on the <em>log</em> half of that hinge.</p>

<p><a href="http://files.justinpickard.net/images/log/2023-04-20-binnacle.jpg" class="web-link"><img class="img-padded" src="http://files.justinpickard.net/images/log/2023-04-20-binnacle.jpg" alt="Compass in binnacle, George Stebbing, 1819"></a></p>

<p>As a format and genre, the weblog is haunted by the ship’s log. Initially, this was a record of readings from the chip log; a piece of wood on a length of rope, used to calculate a ship’s speed. And both of these logs frequently found their way into the binnacle.</p>

<p>Originally a kind of open cupboard, the binnacle usually had separate compartments for compass, lamp, and hourglass — a composite interface of handheld tools, permitting the seafarer to orient themselves (and their vessel) in space and time.</p>

<p>Beyond its actual use, the binnacle was a convenient container for ship documents and equipment of all kinds:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>‘Captain Cook kept the keys of the leg-irons in the binnacle, while Captain Bligh thought his a suitable stowage for a pair of pistols.’ (May, 1954: 28)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The ship’s log existed alongside navigation devices, and ‘within the drifts of other documents on board a typical ship’ (Schotte, 2013: 284). More prominent than other written media, it was neither outlier nor exception — only important inasmuch as it enabled (successful) navigation. Initially intended for personal use during voyages, 16th- and 17th-century log-keepers sought flexibility and simplicity, from a ‘methodical, concise, and adaptable document, validated by daily use’ (ibid: 292).</p>

<p>These navigator-practitioners adopted the ship’s log to cope with ‘increasing quantities of information … in an age when the scale of their oceanic crossings required them to coordinate ever more information’ (Schotte, 2013: 290). But as anthropologist Nick Seaver notes, stories about information overload are as much about shifts in the ‘scalar relationship between archives and individuals’ as any shared, objective reality:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>‘Overload requires more than an overwhelming amount of stuff; it requires someone to feel overwhelmed’ (Seaver, 2023: 36-37)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In a context of information overload, thinking with the binnacle shows how the blog, like the ship’s log, is an epistemic genre; a class or category of texts linked (in their authors’ eyes, at least) to the dance of knowledge-making. (see <a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/lm.2014.0010" class="web-link">Pomata, 2014</a>) For me, the motivation is less about ‘<a href="https://www.robinsloan.com/lab/new-avenues/" class="web-link">working with the garage door open</a>’ than logging an itinerary — discerning and recording information, as a personal navigation aid; and for the benefit of those traversing the same (or similarly) turbulent waters.</p>

<hr>

<h4 id="readings">Readings</h4>

<p>Ganz, J. (2023, February 10). <a href="https://johnganz.substack.com/p/have-you-heard-about-the-polycrisis" class="web-link">Have you heard about “the polycrisis,” yet?</a> <em>Unpopular Front</em>.</p>

<p>May, W. E. (1954). The binnacle. <em>The Mariner’s Mirror</em> 40 (1): 21–32. 🔒<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/00253359.1954.10658189" class="web-link">https://doi.org/10.1080/00253359.1954.10658189</a></p>

<p>Pomata, G. (2014). The medical case narrative: Distant reading of an epistemic genre. <em>Literature and Medicine</em> 32 (1): 1–23. 🔒<a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/lm.2014.0010" class="web-link">https://doi.org/10.1353/lm.2014.0010</a></p>

<p>Schotte, M. (2013). Expert records: Nautical logbooks from Columbus to Cook. <em>Information &amp; Culture</em> 48 (3): 281–322. 🔒<a href="https://doi.org/10.7560/IC48301" class="web-link">https://doi.org/10.7560/IC48301</a></p>

<p>Seaver, N. (2023). <em><a href="https://bookwyrm.social/book/643976/s/computing-taste" class="web-link">Computing Taste: Algorithms and the Makers of Music Recommendation</a></em>, University of Chicago Press, Chicago.</p>

<p>Sloan, R. (2022, December). <a href="https://www.robinsloan.com/lab/new-avenues/" class="web-link">A year of new avenues</a>. <em>Lab Newsletter</em>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Justin Pickard</name></author><category term="meta" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[To stain the blank page: on blogging and the ship’s log, through the figure of the binnacle.]]></summary></entry></feed>