<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jcalpickard.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://jcalpickard.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-05-17T10:33:10-05:00</updated><id>https://jcalpickard.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">⧉</title><subtitle>Notes and log entries, for now.</subtitle><author><name>Justin Pickard</name></author><entry><title type="html">Engrossed: 2024-W20</title><link href="https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/05/17/engrossed-2024-w20/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Engrossed: 2024-W20" /><published>2024-05-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-05-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/05/17/engrossed-2024-w20</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/05/17/engrossed-2024-w20/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="found-myself-in-a-machine-facilitated-fugue-this-week-head-down-puzzling-my-way-through-new-technical-and-conceptual-terrain-with-a-few-video-calls-anchoring-me-to-a-shared-social-reality">Found myself in a machine-facilitated fugue this week; head-down, puzzling my way through new (technical and conceptual) terrain, with a few video calls anchoring me to a shared social reality.</h4>

<h5 id="undertakings">
<strong>Undertakings</strong>:</h5>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Web development</strong>: A frankly inadvisible amount of website-wrangling throughout this week, including some late-night rabbit-holes and debugging loops. I’m now most of the way through an LLM-supported rebuild, shifting my site away from Wordpress to a Jekyll static site.<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote web-link" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> With outside machine support, I’ve been getting more comfortable with working in the command line, Visual Studio Code, etc., and have successfully implemented wiki-style linking, tagging, and a backlinking system, and got an auto-populated rudimentary vis.js knowledge graph up and running.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Latent Intimacies</strong> Check-in with <a href="https://vjnks.com/" class="web-link">Vytas</a> on Tuesday evening, synchronising our thinking about how to develop some of the outcomes of the “Synthetic Minds” collaborative prototyping residency we were part of back in January-February; also helped him think through some text for an (unrelated) publication later in the week.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Choreographing attention</strong>: IM meeting with M (dialling in from a electric vehicle charging station somewhere in Croatia), postponed after I spread myself a bit too thinly last week; talked through plans for getting stuck into the next <a href="https://fo.am/activities/anarchive/" class="web-link">Anarchive</a> Reader, committing to a focused two-week writing-and-editing sprint from the 27th over the more thinly-spread, partial approach we’ve been taking up to now.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Enxaneta</strong>: Week twoish of a planned six-month Python-for-ethnography collaborative skill exchange with <a href="https://www.timcowlishaw.co.uk/" class="web-link">Tim</a>; reflecting on some on my website-wrangling experiences, and the outcomes of a <a href="https://github.com/timcowlishaw/enxaneta/blob/main/documentation/ethnography/01_ethnographic-observation.md" class="web-link">field observation exercise</a> I’d set; talked a bit about critical technical practice, Britishness abroad, Mariann Vaczi’s monograph <em>Catalonia’s Human Towers</em>, and different approaches to bounding and specifying ethnographic fieldsites, setting some next steps for the coming weeks.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><img src="https://files.justinpickard.net/images/log/2024/05/Tim-habia-dithered.png" alt="Tim, Habia etc., dithered"></p>

<h5 id="side-missions">
<strong>Side-missions</strong>:</h5>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Dowsing</strong>: Caught an afternoon screening of <em><a href="https://www.inverse.com/entertainment/la-chimera-review-digital-release" class="web-link">La Chimera</a></em> with D over the weekend, which was shaggy and weird, with a dreamy energy that seeped into the rest of the week. Now imagining a dowsing-specific double feature, running it alongside Ben Wheatly’s <em>A Field in England</em>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Mind the gap</strong>: Social catch-up with <a href="https://www.richardsandford.net/about/" class="web-link">Richard</a>. We’d been in close contact during a flurry of activity putting together an (unsuccessful) funding proposal for a small project on ecological citizenship earlier in the year, and we’re both going to be at <a href="https://anticipationconference.org/" class="web-link">Anticipation</a> in September, so useful to get a sense of the kinds of things he’s thinking about (<a href="https://www.richardsandford.net/2024/04/24/thick-present-in-trento/" class="web-link">※</a>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>On the jagged frontier</strong>: Monthly Friday morning call with <a href="https://andrewlb.com/" class="web-link">Andrew</a>, a little unfocused after staying up into the early hours wrestling with GitHub branches; a wide-ranging chat, covering Wardley maps of dog-breeding as a service, generative AI’s <a href="https://www.hbs.edu/faculty/Pages/item.aspx?num=64700" class="web-link">jagged frontier</a>, the <em>Tao of Pooh</em>, and the ‘protocolisation of small team collaboration’ (whatever that means).</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h5 id="next-week">
<strong>Next week</strong>:</h5>

<ul>
  <li>Shift from technical web development to tweaking the site’s look and feel, and thinking about content strategy</li>
  <li>Another skill exchange session with Tim, going deeper on participant observation and fieldnotes</li>
  <li>Editing work, sketching some ‘serving suggestions’ for a deconstructed photo book</li>
  <li>Call about an archiving/experimental publishing side-mission</li>
</ul>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Don’t talk to me about GitHub branches. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote web-link" role="doc-backlink">⤴︎</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Justin Pickard</name></author><category term="weeknotes" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Found myself in a machine-facilitated fugue this week; head-down, puzzling my way through new (technical and conceptual) terrain, with a few video calls anchoring me to a shared social reality. Undertakings:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Choices about what is salient</title><link href="https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/01/06/choices-about-what-is-salient/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Choices about what is salient" /><published>2024-01-06T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2024-01-06T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/01/06/choices-about-what-is-salient</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2024/01/06/choices-about-what-is-salient/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="a-couple-of-paragraphs-from-the-phd-thesis-unravelling-context-having-drawn-too-close-to-the-large-language-model-and-been-spaghettified">A couple of paragraphs from the <a href="../../../../../phd" class="web-link">PhD thesis</a>, unravelling context, having drawn too close to the <a href="http://ai.stanford.edu/blog/understanding-incontext/" class="web-link">large language model</a> and been <a href="https://science.nasa.gov/universe/what-happens-when-something-gets-too-close-to-a-black-hole/" class="web-link">spaghettified</a>.</h4>

<blockquote>
  <p>Context often appears as an explanatory staple and normative imperative; a self-evident, black-boxed set of ‘external circumstances’ to which objects must yield (Woolgar and Lezaun, 2013). In his writings on context-aware computing, Paul Dourish takes a different approach, differentiating between <em>representational</em> and <em>interactional</em> interpretations of context (Dourish, 2004). In representational accounts, context denotes the features of a given setting. For interactionalists, however, context is something people <em>do</em>; a localised achievement, with tangible material effects, actively produced through social practice (Seaver, 2015: 1105; Asdal and Moser, 2012: 294; Dourish, 2004: 22). Where calls to contextualise typically assume issues and objects are separate from their surroundings, ‘establishing context’ is a <em>political</em> project, bound up with questions of method and practice (Seaver, 2015: 1106). Since, for interactionalists, context is not self-evident, any analysis of the boundaries between context and content entails choices about what is salient, and ‘where the work of contextualization should cease.’ (ibid.)</p>

  <p>For anthropologists, an early emphasis on holism and local field sites has, in recent decades, yielded to a relational understanding of context as comprising a ‘set of <em>connections</em> between the object of inquiry and its surroundings.’ (Morita, 2014: 215) As anthropologist Nick Seaver observes, while ‘it is common sense that to put things <em>in context</em> is good and to take them out of context is <em>bad</em>’, this has often overshadowed disagreements over what, exactly, context <em>is</em> (Seaver, 2015: 1105). At the same time, much work in STS has been shaped by an imperative to avoid either explaining science by its own internal logic or reducing it to a function of its social environments (cf. Asdal and Moser, 2012). In both fields, a once-common explanatory recourse to context has faltered, finding ‘nothing “beyond” [or outside] with which to explain something else.’ (ibid: 295)</p>
</blockquote>

<hr>

<h4 id="readings">Readings</h4>

<p>Asdal, K., &amp; Moser, I. (2012). Experiments in context and contexting. <em>Science, Technology, &amp; Human Values</em>, 37(4), 291–306. 🔒<a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00779-003-0253-8" class="web-link">https://doi.org/10.1177/0162243912449749</a></p>

<p>Dourish, P. (2004). What we talk about when we talk about context. <em>Personal and Ubiquitous Computing</em>, 8(1), 19–30. 🔒<a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00779-003-0253-8" class="web-link">https://doi.org/10.1007/s00779-003-0253-8</a></p>

<p>Fabian, J. (1995). Ethnographic misunderstanding and the perils of context. <em>American Anthropologist</em>, 97(1), 41–50. 🔒<a href="https://doi.org/10.1525/aa.1995.97.1.02a00080" class="web-link">https://doi.org/10.1525/aa.1995.97.1.02a00080</a></p>

<p>Law, J., &amp; Moser, I. (2012). Contexts and culling. <em>Science, Technology, &amp; Human Values</em>, 37(4), 332–354. 🔒<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0162243911425055" class="web-link">https://doi.org/10.1177/0162243911425055</a></p>

<p>Morita, A. (2014). The ethnographic machine: Experimenting with context and comparison in Strathernian ethnography. <em>Science, Technology, &amp; Human Values</em>, 39(2), 214–235. 🔒<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0162243913503189" class="web-link">https://doi.org/10.1177/0162243913503189</a></p>

<p>Seaver, N. (2015). The nice thing about context is that everyone has it. <em>Media, Culture &amp; Society</em>, 37(7), 1101–1109. 🔒<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0163443715594102" class="web-link">https://doi.org/10.1177/0163443715594102</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Justin Pickard</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A couple of paragraphs from the PhD thesis, unravelling context, having drawn too close to the large language model and been spaghettified.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Binnacle</title><link href="https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2023/04/20/binnacle/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Binnacle" /><published>2023-04-20T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-04-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2023/04/20/binnacle</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jcalpickard.github.io/log/2023/04/20/binnacle/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="to-stain-the-blank-page-on-blogging-and-the-ships-log-through-the-figure-of-the-binnacle">To stain the blank page: on blogging and the ship’s log, through the figure of the binnacle.</h4>

<p>What is it to <del>start</del> resume blogging now, in the spring of 2023? (Other than it no longer being 1998, that is.) It seems uncertainty is the order of the day. Some speak of a “<a href="https://www.unpopularfront.news/p/have-you-heard-about-the-polycrisis" class="web-link">polycrisis</a>”, while bracing for further ruptures amid mounting turbulence. The digital leviathans founder, the public sphere takes damage, giving way to a froth of invite-only backchannels and social dark pools. Early ripples, perhaps, of <a href="https://www.are.na/justin-pickard/epistemic-breakdown" class="web-link">epistemic breakdown</a>; a peeling-apart of our criteria for appraising truth amid information overload, new synthetic media, and a multiply-breached social contract.</p>

<p>Today, the web is no longer new media, but the backdrop, staging, and atmospherics of lives lived online. Blog is a clipping of a kenning, hinging the network and the archive. And if the novelty of the web is fast-fading, then we should be places more stress on the <em>log</em> half of that hinge.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/2023-04-20-binnacle.jpg" alt="Compass in binnacle, George Stebbing, 1819"></p>

<p>As a format and genre, the weblog is haunted by the ship’s log. Initially, this was a record of readings from the chip log; a piece of wood on a length of rope, used to calculate a ship’s speed. And both of these logs frequently found their way into the binnacle.</p>

<p>Originally a kind of open cupboard, the binnacle usually had separate compartments for compass, lamp, and hourglass — a composite interface of handheld tools, permitting the seafarer to orient themselves (and their vessel) in space and time.</p>

<p>Beyond its actual use, the binnacle was a convenient container for ship documents and equipment of all kinds:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>‘Captain Cook kept the keys of the leg-irons in the binnacle, while Captain Bligh thought his a suitable stowage for a pair of pistols.’ (May, 1954: 28)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The ship’s log existed alongside navigation devices, and ‘within the drifts of other documents on board a typical ship’ (Schotte, 2013: 284). More prominent than other written media, it was neither outlier nor exception — only important inasmuch as it enabled (successful) navigation. Initially intended for personal use during voyages, 16th- and 17th-century log-keepers sought flexibility and simplicity, from a ‘methodical, concise, and adaptable document, validated by daily use’ (ibid: 292).</p>

<p>These navigator-practitioners adopted the ship’s log to cope with ‘increasing quantities of information … in an age when the scale of their oceanic crossings required them to coordinate ever more information’ (Schotte, 2013: 290). But as anthropologist Nick Seaver notes, stories about information overload are as much about shifts in the ‘scalar relationship between archives and individuals’ as any shared, objective reality:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Overload requires more than an overwhelming amount of stuff; it requires someone to feel overwhelmed (Seaver, 2023: 36-37).</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In a context of information overload, thinking with the binnacle shows how the blog, like the ship’s log, is an epistemic genre; a class or category of texts linked (in their authors’ eyes, at least) to the dance of knowledge-making. (see <a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/lm.2014.0010" class="web-link">Pomata, 2014</a>) For me, the motivation is less about ‘<a href="https://www.robinsloan.com/lab/new-avenues/" class="web-link">working with the garage door open</a>’ than logging an itinerary — discerning and recording information, as a personal navigation aid; and for the benefit of those traversing the same (or similarly) turbulent waters.</p>

<hr>

<h4 id="readings">Readings</h4>

<p>Ganz, J. (2023, February 10). <a href="https://johnganz.substack.com/p/have-you-heard-about-the-polycrisis" class="web-link">Have you heard about “the polycrisis,” yet?</a> <em>Unpopular Front</em>.</p>

<p>May, W. E. (1954). The binnacle. <em>The Mariner’s Mirror</em> 40 (1): 21–32. 🔒<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/00253359.1954.10658189" class="web-link">https://doi.org/10.1080/00253359.1954.10658189</a></p>

<p>Pomata, G. (2014). The medical case narrative: Distant reading of an epistemic genre. <em>Literature and Medicine</em> 32 (1): 1–23. 🔒<a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/lm.2014.0010" class="web-link">https://doi.org/10.1353/lm.2014.0010</a></p>

<p>Schotte, M. (2013). Expert records: Nautical logbooks from Columbus to Cook. <em>Information &amp; Culture</em> 48 (3): 281–322. 🔒<a href="https://doi.org/10.7560/IC48301" class="web-link">https://doi.org/10.7560/IC48301</a></p>

<p>Seaver, N. (2023). <em><a href="https://bookwyrm.social/book/643976/s/computing-taste" class="web-link">Computing Taste: Algorithms and the Makers of Music Recommendation</a></em>, University of Chicago Press, Chicago.</p>

<p>Sloan, R. (2022, December). <a href="https://www.robinsloan.com/lab/new-avenues/" class="web-link">A year of new avenues</a>. <em>Lab Newsletter</em>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Justin Pickard</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[To stain the blank page: on blogging and the ship’s log, through the figure of the binnacle.]]></summary></entry></feed>